<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe relation by the commoners in Lincolnshire of their legall interest, and that nothing of interest the vndertakers have in law.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102840</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838602</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe relation by the commoners in Lincolnshire of their legall interest, and that nothing of interest the vndertakers have in law.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 17-20   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Begins with leaf C1.</note>
                  <note>Not an STC item.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fens, The(England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lincolnshire(England) --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div n="legal interest" type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:2986:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2986:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>A Breefe Relation by the Commoners in Lincolnſhire, of their Legall Intereſt, and that nothing of Intereſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers have in Law.</head>
            <p>The owners and Commoners in the Fenns, between Bourn &amp; Kyme Fae in the County of Lincoln, by reaſon of their Seniories, Reſiances, and Inhabitants in the Townes, there, have time out of minde, without memory of man, taken all manner of profits ariſing out of the ſaid Fenns and Commons, both for ſuſtentation of their perſons and Common of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for their Cattell, (as appurtenant to their Seniores and Reſiances, and are, and ever have been (by Cuſtome) char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by reaſon of their Seniories, with the repairing of many Draines, Watercourſes, Banks, Sleuces, and Goats, for the bettering and making them ſo uſefull for them, and for watering ſeverall grounds in many of the ſaid Townſhips, which they have been much interrupted in by ſeverall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers this twenty years in making of new workes, a deſigne continued at Court to deprive us of our ancient Rights, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and againſt the known Lawes of the Land.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the 9. <hi>H.</hi> 3. cap. 15. no Free-man ſhall be diſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make Banks,<note place="margin">Magna Charta.</note> but ſuch as were of old time and of right have been accuſtomed to make them in the time of K. H. our Grandfather.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2986:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <p n="2">2. Alſo in the 16. Chap the ſame year provides that no Bancks ſhall be defended from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forth, but ſuch as were in defence in the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dfather, by the ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds as they were in his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me.</p>
            <p>By the 15. and 16 Chapters the U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dertaker ſhall not tax me for any ground to make new Banks that before were not in charge.</p>
            <p>This is manifeſted to be the true meaning of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> by the ſucceeding Statute <hi>(viz.)</hi> the 25. and 45. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>R.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 4. and eſpecially the 12. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>By the 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. chap. 5. the workes and words mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 6. and 7. Chapters of the 12. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. were united and knit up in one ſtanding Commiſſion, commonly called a Commiſſion of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wers, and all thoſe words and workes are ſubject to the Survey of the Commiſſioners mentioned in that Statute of 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. But thereby the workes and words mentioned in the 6. chap. 12. <hi>E.</hi> 4 are to be purſued as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the 6 <hi>H.</hi> 6. chap. 5. and the faults and words mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 7. chap. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. are to be purſued according as is ſet forth in the 7 Chapter; for it is commanded by the ſayd 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. that the Juſtices ſhall doe therein as to the Kings Juſtices appertaineth, after the Lawes and Statutes of our Realme, which includes the ſayd 6 and 7. chap. <hi>E.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Obſerve the Undertakers proceeded not by Jury, but by directions of the Kings Letters.</note> The practice is, and ought to be by Jury thus; is there a Delinquent found by Inquiſition upon the ſubſtance of the 6 chap. of <hi>Edw</hi> 4? Let the Commiſſioners proceed againſt him for the repaire, or making new that which is ſo found to be hurtfull in his default<note n="*" place="margin">They layd uncertaine tax: upon no body: of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it might not be payed.</note> by a tax, aſſeſſe, diſtreſſe, or ſale.</p>
            <p>Is there a Delinquent found by Inquiſition upon the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance mentioned in the 7. chap. of <hi>Edw</hi> 4? Let them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them by giving them by <hi>ſcire facies,</hi> halfe a years time to remove or correct the ſayd nuſance as the Juſtices ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt upon paine of 100 Marke to be eſtreated.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the power of Commiſſioners by the 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. chap. 5. is limited in matter of fact by the former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the 6. and 7. chap. of <hi>E.</hi> 4. and they are limited in matter of forme by the words of the 23. <hi>H.</hi> 5. which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2986:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->them to doe as belongs to the Kings Juſtices accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Statutes of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now if Commiſſioners of Sewers be tyed to this matter of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t and forme, examine how the Undertakers by their new Law can take our Inheritance, without our conſent and li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, to make new Draines, Banks, and Goats, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying their owne covetous deſires, notwithſtanding theſe limitations the innovating Undertakers would ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds in the ſayd 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>viz.</hi> according to your diſcretions, and according to the Lawes of Rumney-Marſh in that Statute expreſſed, implying by the word diſcretion, that they may doe what they pleaſe; which gloſſe confounds the text, for ſuch diſcretion is abſolute and apparent indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not ſupportable by that Statute, nor any other Law, their diſcretions being to be guided by Law and Cuſtome, as formerly expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And as concerning their imaginary proceedings according to the Lawes of Rumney-Marſh, that is moſt ridiculous; for I pray you obſerve the Charter granted the 36. yeare of <hi>H.</hi> 3. to the men of Rumney-Marſh, and you will finde that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is granted, but what was time out of minde in uſe (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting a reſtraint to the Shiriffe for medling with diſtreſſes.)</p>
            <p>Hereby yee ſee Cuſtome time out of minde begets a Rule, and was the ground of this Charter, which Charter was the ground of the Commiſſion of 42. <hi>H.</hi> 3. to <hi>Hen. Bathama,</hi> to ſurvey the Walls and Water Courſes, and to cauſe them to be repaired by theſe that are bound and charged with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of them; here is <hi>nihil novi,</hi> but <hi>de novo,</hi> as accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be repaired or new made, agreeing to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> above ſpecified.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the projects of drayning hath no foot hold or congruency with Cuſtome, uſe, or any Law or word of Statute before recited, but is a meare Arbitrary proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Lawes.</p>
            <p>They plead that they have layd out vaſt ſummes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2986:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <p>To this I heare ſome mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Note that before the <hi>43 Eliz.</hi> there was no generall Act for drayning. <hi>Tyndalls, 4. Jac.</hi> was a particular Act, and there are ſome other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular grounds, whereby it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that without a ſpeciall directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Statute, or without the power of the ſaid <hi>43. Eliz.</hi> no perſon is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by the <hi>33. H. 8.</hi> chap. <hi>5.</hi> or any other Statute to undertake that deſigne, for if otherwiſe the ſayd <hi>43. Eliz.</hi>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tyndalls, 4. Jac.</hi> and ſome other Statutes for Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſteed Marſh, <hi>23. Eliz.</hi> were to be judged Acts to no purpoſe made.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>caveat Empt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for him to expect a Parliament ſuccor herein, when as he hath utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waved and rejected the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment direction, which appeares to be given him by the words of 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> chap. 11. wherein all draynings are graciouſly provided for, both to the content of the Parties intereſſed, and alſo for the due and fit recompence to the Undertaker, he hath thus ſpurred againſt a Parliamentall courſe, why ſhould he now hope for a Parliament redreſſe to maintaine his Arbitrary Courſe, which will reach Hills and Mountaines, when we have no more low Grounds left to ſatisfie their covetous deſires.</p>
            <p>That abuſes to the Perſons, Goods, Lands, Draynes, Goats and Banks, I leave to the Expreſſion of the ſeverall Petitions exhibited by them that are grieved and oppreſſed by the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2986:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
